Guide to the Daughters of the American Revolution Blacklist controversy Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Daughters of the American Revolution Blacklist controversy papers
1921-1930
SC0063
Stanford University
0.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Anonymous gift, 1969
Information about Access
None.
HISTORICAL NOTE
In 1928, Mrs. Helen Tufts Bailie wrote an article accusing the Daughters of the American Revolution of circulating a "blacklist" of men and women who would not be welcome as speakers before D.A.R. members. The "blacklisted" people were accused of being Communists, Socialists, liberals, pacifists. Among those blacklisted by the D.A.R. was David Starr Jordan, former president of Stanford University. Many D.A.R. members and others protested the blacklist. Finally the Palo Alto chapter of the D.A.R. resigned their membership in the national organization.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
Included in this collection are pamphlets, newspaper clippings, magazine articles and correspondence dealing with the D.A.R. blacklist controversy.
Access Terms
Daughters of the American Revolution.
Collection Contents
- Articles (Folder 1)
  - "Our Threatened Heritage", by Helen Tufts Bailie, 5-Apr-28
  - "Truth and Justice vs. the DAR Court Martial", by Helen Tufts Bailie, 23-Jun-28
  - "Perverted Patriotism, A Story of DAR Stewardship", 11-Nov-29
  - "Are DAR Women Exploited?", by Elaine Goodale Eastmen, 11-Sep-29
  - "Dishonoring the DAR", by Helen Tufts Bailie, 25-Sep-29
- Correspondence, 1928 (Folder 2)
  - T.L.S.: David Starr Jordan to Miss Helen E. Crumpton, Corresponding Secretary, Palo Alto Chapter DAR, re: expressing thanks for their support during "Blacklist" issue, 14-May-28
  - T.L. Jane Addams to Jessie K. Jordan, re: DAR's attack on Helen Tufts Bailie, June 14, 1928
  - affidavit, signed by May M. Glotfelter re: receipt of "blacklist" from DAR official, June 19, 1928
  - T.L.S. May M. Glotfelter to Jessie K. Jordan, re: blacklist, July 9, 1928
  - T.L.S. May M. Glotfelter to Jessie K. Jordan, re: blacklist, July 13, 1928
  - T.L.S. Josepha Whitney to Mrs. Jordan, re: possible resignations from DAR, July 24, 1928
  - T.L.S. Elaine Goodale Eastmen, re: support for those blacklisted by DAR, August 10, 1928
  - T.L.S. Helen Tufts Bailie to Mrs. Jordan, re: DAR blacklist, August 31, 1928
  - T.L. Resolution supporting Republican candidate for President of U.S., September 12, 1928
  - T.L. Elaine Goodale Eastmen, Newsletter, re: progress of fight against blacklist, September 27, 1928
  - A.L.S. Jeannette M. Hitchcock to Dr. Clelia Duel Mosher, re: newspaper articles concerning blacklist, October 4, 1928
  - T.L.S. Jane Norman Smith, Nation Woman's Party, support for Hoover for President, and equal rights for women, October 8, 1928
- Correspondence, 1929 (Folder 3)
  - T.L. Mrs. Julius to Mrs. McEven, re: DAR constitution and voting rights at national annual meetings., January 5, 1929
  - T.L.S. Elaine Goodale Eastmen, newsletter re: progress of fight against DAR blacklist, April 6, 1929
  - A.L.S. Mary Ella Thurston to David Starr Jordan, re: DAR blacklist, June 4, 1929
  - A.L.S. Jessie K. Jordan to Dr. Clelia Mosher, re: getting all material distributed by Elaine Goodale Eastman., October, 1929
  - T.L. Resolution supporting David Starr Jordan, by DAR Palo Alto Chapter, November 11, 1929
  - T.L. S. Riverside, California chapter DAR to David Starr Jordan re: support of his peace effort, November 13, 1929
- Correspondence, 1930 (Folder 4)
  - T.L., twelve members of Palo Alto chapter DAR submit their resignations, May 15, 1930
  - T.L.S. Fred Lawrence Foster to the ladies of DAR, Palo Alto chapter, re: need to protect America against "Jewrissia" and warmongering Zionists, May 16, 1930
  - T.L. Mrs. Lowell Fletcher Hobart, President General DAR to Mrs. C.W. Neff, Regent, Palo Alto chapter DAR, re: Palo Alto Chapter resignation, June 16, 1930
- Correspondence relating to the Lewis and Clark Oregon chapter of the DAR and its condemnation of the National DAR's blacklist, 1928 (Folder 5)
- Letters by Mary P. MacFarland, 1928 (Folder 6)
  - "To the Members of the Daughters of the American Revolution..." by Mary P. MacFarland, March 10, 1928
  - "To the Members of the D.A.R.", by Mary P. MacFarland., April 5, 1928
  - Mary P. MacFarland, re: undemocratic character of DAR, September 28, 1928
- Clippings, 1928-1930 (Folder 7)
  - New York World, "Inquiry Points to Spy System Muzzling U. S.", Feb 12 1928
  - New York World, "Heresy Hunters' Blacklist Seen to Cover Wide Range"., Feb 13 1928
  - New York World, "Maude Royden's Socialism Basis of Attack on Her", Feb 14 1928
  - New York World, "Ready Reference List of Heretics; Sins Catalogued", Feb 15 1928
  - New York World, "Blacklists Spur Patriot Bodies to Bar Speakers", Feb 16 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "DAR Leader Attacks 'Blacklisting' Policy", Apr 2 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Adds Notables to its Blacklist", Apr 4 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Head in Klan Nightie, Says Editor", Apr 5 1928
  - Emporia Weekly Gazette, "The Horselaugh of the Free, Apr 5 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Rulers Called Dupes of Anti-Reds", Apr 9 1928
  - Emporia Weekly Gazette, "Mr. White Replies", Apr 12 1928
  - Washington Post, "DAR Regents Praise Activities for Defense", Apr 15 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "Recent Clouds in DAR Sky Hang Over National Convention; President to Speak Tonight", Apr 16 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "President to Open Meeting of DAR Today", Apr 16 1928
  - Washington Post, "Campaign is Begun for DAR Election by 4,000 Delegates", Apr 16 1928
  - Washington Post, "President Pleads for Rule of People won in Revolution", Apr 17 1928
  - unknown, "Americanism", Apr 17 1928
  - unknown, picture, Apr 18 1928
  - unknown, "Rebellion Against Blacklist of DAR Breaks in Conclave", Apr 19 1928
  - Washington Post, "Immigration Work of DAR Praised by James J. Davis", Apr 19 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "Blacklist Sustained by DAR", Apr 20 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Session Names Seven New Leaders", Apr 20 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Rebel Loses Orders for Emblems", Apr 21 1928
  - Springfield Weekly Republican, "DAR Backs `Black Lists' by Inference", Apr 26 1928
  - unknown, "DAR Launches Ouster Move on 'Black List' Foe", Apr 27 1928
  - New York Times, "DAR Lays Charges Against Mrs. Bailey", Apr 28 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "DAR Insurgent Chief Who Bared 'Blacklist' Now Faces Discipline", Apr 28 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Torn in Blacklist Row; Eleven Resign", May 2 1928
  - Emporia Weekly Gazette, "Lady Sheep", May 3 1928
  - Eugene, Oregon, paper, "A Rubber Stamp Without a User, May 15 1928
  - Manchester Guardian, "U.S.A. Patriots", May 15 1928
  - Manchester Guardian, "Professional Patriots of the U.S.A.", May 18 1928
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR's Ban Blacklist", May 26 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "DAR Blackballs Member as Result of 'Blacklist' Affair", June 23 1928
  - Redwood City Tribune, "Blacklist Not in Use by 'Key Men' Says Chief in His Answer to Charges", July 19 1928
  - Emporia Weekly Gazette, "Kansas in the DAR Row", Nov 11 1928
  - New York Times, "DAR Blacklisters Called 'Blue Menace"', Dec l 1928
  - Fort Wayne Sentinel News, "Hoover Not to Address DAR", Apr 12 1928
  - Palo Alto Times, "DAR Refuse to Reinstate Ousted Woman", Apr 16 1929
  - Washington Post, "6,000 Take Part In Reception Given to Mrs. Brosseau", Apr 18 1929
  - unknown, "Woman Who Ruffled DAR Feathers is Courageous", Apr 22 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Leaders Urged to War on 'New Ring' by Mrs. Catt", July 5, 1929
  - Christian Century, "Are DAR Women Exploited?", Sep 11 1929
  - Nation, "Dishonoring the DAR", Sep 25 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Pastor Flays DAR as Tools, Accessories of Shearer", Oct 7 1929
  - Palo Alto Times, "Women to Study Navy Construction Program", Oct 23 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Jordan Hailed Peace Prophet", Nov 2 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Many Candidates Loom on Horizon for DAR Election in May ", Nov 3 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Dr. Jordan Wins Praise from DAR", Nov 5 1929
  - San Francisco Examiner, "Palo Alto Group, Which Did Not Join Attack of Scholar, Praises His Work for Peace", Nov 5 1929
  - Stanford Daily, "Dr. Jordan and the DAR's", Nov 8 1929
  - Palo Alto Times, "Jordan Tells DAR Delegation Peace Will Ultimately Triumph", Nov 11 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Chapter Honors Dr. Jordan as Outstanding Champion of World Peace", Nov 12 1929
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Member Resigns over Blacklisting", Feb 9 1930
  - San Francisco Examiner, "Brig. Gen. Reilly Flays Pacifists in Radio Talk", Feb 28 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Drys Force Issue in State DAR", Mar l 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Chester Rowell's Comment", Mar 12 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Chester Rowell's Comment", Apr 14 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Fights Hoover Plan For Reduction of Defenses", Apr 17 1930
  - Stanford Daily, "DAR Finger in the Pie", Apr 18 1930
  - New York Times, "DAR Resignations Laid to Pacifism", Apr 20 1930
  - Palo Alto Times, "Local Leaders Bolt DAR", May 15 1930
  - New York Times, "Half in Stanford Unit Quit DAR in Protest", May 15 1930
  - Palo Alto Times, "Local Secession of DAR Group Stirs National President", May 16 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Twelve Palo Altans Quit DAR in Board Protest", May 16 1930
  - San Francisco Examiner, "Head of DAR Say 'Bolters' Out of Touch", May 16 1930
  - Stanford Daily, "DAR Members of Palo Alto Score Policies", May 16 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Mrs. Jordan Tells Why 12 Quit DAR", May 17 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Board Acts Assailed", May 17 1930
  - Palo Alto Times, "Rebels Descendants Show Varying Traits", May 16 1930
  - Palo Alto Times, "New DAR Exodus in State Looming", May 20 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Walkout Threatened by Californians", May 20 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Public Airing of DAR Row Being Sought", May 21 1930
  - Tacoma News Tribune, "DAR Disapprove Defense Body Policies", May 30, n y
  - Palo Alto Times, "DAR Leaders Seem to See Their Course in Question", June 10 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "National DAR Head Sends Out An Explanation", June 22 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "DAR Shows Membership Gain Despite Withdrawals", June 30 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Mrs. Maddux Resigns from DAR", July 3 1930
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Communism in Wisconsin University? What of it? 'Prexy' Replies to DAR", Oct 30 1930
  - Los Angeles Times, n. d., "DAR Regent Maps Policies"
  - New York World n.d. "DAR Blacklist"
  - Palo Alto Times, .n.d., "11 DAR Members Quit in Protest of Blacklist"
  - Palo Alto Times, n.d., "DAR Endorses Blacklist"
  - Palo Alto Times, n.d., "DAR Heads Described as 'Dupes"'
  - Palo Alto Times, n.d., "Contest for DAR Presidency to Mark Continental Congress at Washington, D. C. This Week"
  - San Francisco Chronicle, n.d., "Opponents of DAR Chiefs Gain Strength"
  - San Francisco Chronicle, n.d., "Chester Rowell's Comment"
  - San Francisco Chronicle, n.d., "DAR Accused of Alliances with Politics"
  - San Francisco Chronicle, n.d., "DAR Refer Catt Charges to Capital"
  - unknown, n.d., "DAR Talks"
  - unknown, n.d., picture
  - unknown, n.d., "And it May Be That DAR Too Really Favor World Court"
  - unknown, n.d., "DAR Head Makes Reply to Mrs. Catt's Criticisms"
  - unknown, n.d., "DAR Scored in Retter by Suffrage Head"
  - unknown, n.d., "DAR Outlaws to Hold Party"
  - unknown, n.d., "The 'Daughters' and the Fathers"
  - unknown, n.d., "Ouster Movement Against Blacklist Foe of DAR Starts"
  - unknown, n.d., "When Ignorance is Labeled Patriotism"
- "The Common Enemy", date supplied by Key Men of America; it describes how communists, socialists and liberals are trying to destroy America. (Folder 8)
- DAR National Defense Committee; a report made by a committee of the Palo Alto Chapter, DAR. (Folder 9)
- DAR documents and speeches, 1927-1929 (Folder 10)
  - Resolution adopted by the 38th Continental Congress, DAR, April 15-20, 1929
  - DAR Constitution and By-laws, "What the Daughters Do" by Mrs. Alfred J. Brosseau, President General, DAR., 1927
  - "Speech of Acceptance" by Mrs. Alfred J. Brosseau, Pres. Gen. DAR, 16-Apr-29
  - "Address of the Pres. General to the DAR", 15-Apr-29
- "The Blue Menace" by Elizabeth McCausland, Mar, 1928 (Folder 11)
  "A Discussion of the drive against liberalism, the curtailment of free speech in Massachusetts and elsewhere by means of blacklists, the attack on liberal colleges and churches, and the DAR protest"
- DAR Palo Alto Chapter Yearbook, 1926-29 (Folder 12)
- Articles in Periodicals re: DAR "Blacklist" Controversy (Folder 13)
  - The Woman Citizen, "Letter DAR", July, 1927
  - Daughters American Revolution Magazine, "National Defense Committee", April 1928
  - Pax International, "The DAR", April, 1928
  - The Literary Digest, "What is behind the DAR blacklists?", April 14, 1928
  - The Literary Digest, More Light on the DAR blacklists", April 21, 1928; "
  - National Council for Prevention of War News Bulletin, "DAR Governing Board to try Mrs. Bailie", June 1, 1928
  - "Oregon DAR Chapter Repudiates Blacklist"
  - The Christian Leader, "Perverted Patriotism", July 14, 1928
  - National Council for Prevention of War News Bulletin, 'Kellogg Proposal Endorsed by DAR", August 1, 1928
  - The World Tomorrow, "Wanted: A New Scandal Expert", August 1, 1928
  - The American Mercury, "The Soviet of Lady Patriots", September, 1928
  - Harpers Magazine, "What the Blue Menace Means", October, 1928
  - Outlook and Independent,"Mrs. Brosseau and the DAR", March 20, 1929
  - Daughters of the American Revolution Magazine, March, 1929
  - The Christian Century, "Are DAR Women Exploited?", September 11, 1929
  - The Nation, "Dishonoring the DAR", September 25, 1929
  - Time, "Daughters in Arms", April 28, 1930
  - Time, "Races Perish in Peace", May 26, 1930
- Miscellaneous papers, 1921-1928 (Folder 14)
  - Invitation to "Blacklist Party", undated
  - Confidential Information Memorandum for DAR members only....
  - DAR Annual Meeting Resolutions, (1928)
  - A.L.S. Will Irwin to David Starr Jordan re: DAR blacklists, undated
  - More "Red" Alarms, Women's Journal, Nov 28 undated
  - "Pacifism Kept Alive by Fifty Organizations", July 13, 1927
  - "The Maternity Bill", Speech of James A. Reed, in U. S. Senate, June 29, 1921